<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>7H3 M33K 933K 8L09</title><link href="http://takwas.github.io/meekgeek/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://takwas.github.io/meekgeek/feeds/animashaun-tosin-ace-takwas.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://takwas.github.io/meekgeek/</id><updated>2014-08-02T12:07:04+02:00</updated><entry><title>#dgplug Summer Training 2014 - The Journey So Far</title><link href="http://takwas.github.io/meekgeek/dgplug_2014.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-08-02T12:07:04+02:00</updated><author><name>Animashaun Tosin (Ace Takwas)</name></author><id>tag:takwas.github.io,2014-08-02:meekgeek/dgplug_2014.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The 2014 edition of the &lt;em&gt;Dugarpur Linux Users Group&lt;/em&gt;b's (dgplug) Summer Training Program kick started on &lt;em&gt;Sunday, 29:sup:'th'&lt;/em&gt; of June. The program is aimed at grooming programmers (especially &lt;em&gt;greenhorns&lt;/em&gt;) to contribute to community &lt;strong&gt;Free and Open Source Software&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;FOSS&lt;/strong&gt;) projects. It turns out there are hundreds, thousands of projects out there being co-developed by developers who are not even bound by geographical locations. What do you need to attend these sessions? A Linux distro (preferably &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://fedoraproject.org"&gt;Fedora&lt;/a&gt;); and decent internet connection (the classes hold on IRC).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The past eleven &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://irc.lc"&gt;IRC&lt;/a&gt; sessions have indeed proven to be worth the while; the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dgplug.org/irclogs/2014/"&gt;class logs&lt;/a&gt; hold quite the evidence to attest to this. Many of the attendees who often throw-in their votes of thanks invariably after the session moderator formally ends a session by posting the message &lt;em&gt;&amp;lt;-----Session Ends-----&amp;gt;&lt;/em&gt;, will agree to this – no doubt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last two weeks, we've been through quite an array of topics – most of them being fairly new to me. This year's edition kicked off with about three to four sessions devoted to learning various communication tools: &lt;strong&gt;Wikis_, Blogs_, IRC_, and `Mailing Lists`_&lt;/strong&gt; as well as some ethical prescriptions; IRC and &amp;quot;mailing list&amp;quot; primers: use of commands; rules as well as introduction of moderators (not leaving out our bot, 'Batul' (now known as 'Ekanora')). We spent these initial sessions educating ourselves on how to appropriately communicate in the channel (e.g. no SMS Speak; use an exclamation (!) mark to queue-up for asking questions; say '&amp;lt;eof&amp;gt;' when you're done querying, and so on...); not top posting in mailing lists. Basically, these were 'Q and A' sessions, or to put this differently, &lt;em&gt;FAQ build-up&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the progress of the training so far, we've gone through tutorials on Vim(a terminal-based text editor), a bit of the Bourne-Again Shell (BASh), reStructuredText (RST):  a documentation tool that can generate static HTML pages, and Blogging.
Although the organisers deem Fedora fit enough to make it the choice platform for working on (they claim its arguably the best platform for open-source development), I have to commend the moderators for coming well prepared, providing support for other platforms, most notably Canonical's Debian-based distro Ubuntu. This is important because a lot of people are starting off as Linux noobs, and you'd expect that they quintessentially get advised to join the Ubuntu bandwagon for starters. So don't get worried when you see a “sudo yum ...”; someone will most likely post the equivalent “sudo apt-get ...”. (If they don't, simply ask!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mentors have been there to help all the time, at least to the best of their capabilities. Folks like: chandankumar, sayan, rtnpro, Armaggedon, and even kushal himself (Kushal is the organiser of this program). Each of them has taken up at least a session. By the way, rtnpro is the creator of waartar (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://waartar.org"&gt;http://waartar.org&lt;/a&gt;), an IRC client.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worthy of mention are the two inspirational keynote sessions in which moderators: 'chandankumer' and 'sayan' gave their success stories. It turns out these folks have not been in the business for so long - and that goes to show how much progress you can make in so little time, given you're determined, wiling to learn, up and doing, and purposeful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good number of technical 'jargons' have been taught through these sessions, as well as through posted links (and we've had quite a number of those links ;)).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the start and end of each session, we take roll calls for statistical purposes.
Training sessions hold for roughly two hours every weekday; official starting time being 1830hrs IST (that's Indian Standard Time). If this timing is not convenient for you, don't bite yourself; you can read up the class logs to follow along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To join a session:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visit &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://irc.lc/freenode"&gt;http://irc.lc/freenode&lt;/a&gt; within your web browser#&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Login with a username and an optional password. (Hint: You can register a unique username for yourself and have it password protected)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Join the IRC channel: #dgplug&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get an IRC client for your platform (Linux, Mac, Windows, Android, J2ME) like xChat, waarta, qicr...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect with the IRC server: irc.freenode.net:6667&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Join the IRC channel: #dgplug&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</summary></entry></feed>